all right
welcome to this
parallax event my name is thoma mark
i'm the publisher of uh
parallax magazine and um
uh uh phenomenal that's a german
publisher who um specified on philosophy
and spirituality and psychology
um my guest our guest
today is alexander bart he is a
philosopher and a futurist and author
of digital libido amongst others a book
that i just recently published with
finnameen publishing
and i'm very glad that he agreed to
partake on this special event
it will goes like this that
he i will introduce him soon and we will
have a short conversation
and he will do a
short lecture about 40 minutes 45
minutes
and you will have the chance
to answer a
question do do uh um ask him some
questions
um regarding his lecture you can do this
by
writing me in the chat box and
i will give you the
unmute you with zoom basically so you
can have
the chance to talk directly to alexander
bart in
in that moment so i think the whole
event will be around two
two hours maybe for me it's uh kind of
premier also because i also
i i did a couple of podcasts with my
show lateral conversations but this is a
live event and i
don't really know how this all will work
out so
i hope you all will give me some slack
um yeah so i hope um
you will enjoy this evening with
alexander bart which i now
um uh
welcome to the stage alexander are you
there
i'm here yes can you hear me oh i should
have i should have a proper picture
right you should so where where did i
change
that still there
wow okay we won over technology
right okay great it just took five
minutes sorry about that you could
probably edit it afterwards so all of
you guys to get the love feed
you'll get the full-on experience right
everybody watches this later
this will probably be cut out and we'll
go straight to the
micro lecture yeah amazing so how are
you doing alexander i'm very good
actually i'm in a good booty kind of
these problems kind of add some charm to
it i hope they're
participants okay of course no it's the
first time for me so i hope they
cut me some slack and and but you know
since we first met
in in february in paris i have the
feeling that we are
solving those problems on the fly all
the time basically
well we almost died after that meeting
yes that's true
that's true unless you don't know the
story tom and i went out uh we were
seeing andrew sweeney and the three of
us are going out together for a weekend
in paris and we had the most wonderful
time okay this is
this is where the idea of the cigar and
cognac club came along this is like
it's an idea of the men's movement in
europe have adopted now but essentially
the first tigar encounter club was early
february 2020
it was me and you tom and then our
friend andrew and the three of us went
out together in paris
and on sunday night you and i went out
at dinner and we both traced
traced it back to with that when we got
the virus because we were both
pretty ill like two or three weeks later
you a majorica
means sweden and went into isolation i
had a bad boot to copy 19 for like 28
days or something like that during march
and april but it all started
in paris early february but we've
survived
we're around we're hopefully immune and
um looking forward to the post-corona
universe aren't we
yeah exactly and so then then uh
additionally i mean it's it's not really
part of this conversation but then you
know
uh we we started um thinking about
publishing your your books in germany
and you know we did some wonderful
podcasts you know so some mini series
and
you did an amazing series of podcasts
with andrew sweeney and
and so and and it's it's it was a wild
ride
this year and they're all available so
you can all go and check the information
you just basically google andrew sweeney
and alexander broad running
tom and then you find us there right so
and and
it all boils down to parallax so
i'm a huge fan of parallax tom bronze
parallax and andrew runs it with tom so
parallax to me is a perfect example of
like a really contemporary place you can
go online and find tons of really great
materials especially this conversation
that is somewhere between
philosophy politics and spirituality
especially that conversation parallax is
really good at it
you're putting together great work tom
and the fact that we're also now
working from a european basis means that
parallax also now introduces
translations so you can go into this
discourse
it's not just completely anglo-saxon
we're kind of tired of the fact that
so much for people are concerned and
want to talk about these days is just
completely in english
so it's it's either directed from from
the uk or from the us
right but what's great about the kind of
work we do is that we're all based in
continental europe
and we want our translations to other
languages and
thank you for translating digital libido
this is the original english version
right yeah thank you for translating it
so well to german tom so yeah
it's an amazing book i hope you will
talk a little bit about it
i mean it's like with with parallax also
and this is one of the great ideas that
we had in paris with andrew
together that you know it's not just a
magazine but there's also like
in the future like a kind of academy
attached where you can
search and for new content and for new
sense make a way of sense making and
you know and make sense of the kind of
world and mess we we are in right now
and to
you know to find to find a platform
there and that's that's the
general idea we had in paris and so i'm
i'm i'm really happy that
yeah because the all the old
institutions are going to go this is one
of the
central thesis of my work with john cena
quest
uh so we've written five books we're
working on the sixth one
and um the first three books have been
released in lots of different languages
under the title the futurica trilogy
because we're obviously
futurologists and philosophers at the
same time
so we we've done a lot of work on where
are we going where's humanity going next
and obviously he's been writing for like
20 years
we've hit the nail now several times
over so like
um a lot of the things we predicted have
been in our books already we predicted
pandemics would happen and take on a
different scale
in the internet age you know most of
things are happening currently we
predicted before
we rose wrote those three books first
yada and then we continued
now with a new trilogy which probably
when it's all finished is going to be
called the exodus
so it's essentially a philosophy on how
you leave one paradigm of history and
walk into another paradigm
of course the term paradigm is thomas
coons a term for saying a certain
age like a certain age we lived in and
then we move on to another age but of
course all these
histories about exodus like you
you left amer europe going to america
you know the story of the promised land
the hebrews left egypt
all these extras that history are good
metaphors what we're actually going
through right now
except this time we're moving from one
age to another age in history
and one of the central thesis that that
certificate is now working with is that
if you compare the current paradigm
shift
from previous paradigm shifts we
discovered that all
the old institutions and the entire old
power structure of the previous paradigm
will eventually collapse or at least be
marginalized
an interesting thing with something like
parallax here is that parallax is
of course um somewhere between academic
and mass media in in in the terminology
of the old paradigm so
you know you would have media media
would all be mass media
it would be uh the printing press
essentially and its electronic versions
so that would be newspapers radio
television
and all these mass media would be you
know
controlled from above and they were
recognized by the fact that they would
distribute
information you know
very effectively right started system
but with no response
so basically we were told what to do
right so but focusing now more on
digital libido
um um you will have like a lecture now
it's like what's
what's the general topic of uh what you
would talk about
okay so the only situations fall apart
new institutions open up so parallax
that's where we fit in i just want to
say that somewhere between the academia
which is imploding today
and mass videos uploading today so
somewhere between these two
in the online world is where we work at
parallax so
i just want to say that right our
philosophy is tied in with the kind of
work that you do so people
see the connection here okay so you will
give me some half hour or something to
explain this box
just a little bit yeah yeah 40 45
minutes so all right what
what will you be talking about okay
okay now okay i give you the floor
finally the technology works i guess the
floor
yeah i get the and and all of you out
there all you guys out there
please remember if you want to stay on
after i'm finished we're gonna have a
question and answer session and
tom will let you in with your little
face and your name and your voice
and you will then ask a question so we
try to make this work so right
thank you alexander we are all yes you
know
okay so i met john soderlist in 1998.
believe it or not
we knew about each other before we
started writing together but we didn't
know each other
and uh i had an offer i was hired by the
stockholm school of economics in 1998
to give a series of lectures on the
internet and this was like late 1990s
and
once i started studying the topic really
deeply i discovered that
um almost everything we'd assume about
the internet already then was wrong
that might be easy to say now you know
because we have the dot-com boom and
you know a lot of attempts at
understanding internet and frustrating
you know milk it for money or whatever
but most of those projects failed it
turns out that the products that did
succeed and became the tech giants that
we have today
took a much more long-term view and had
a better understanding of what the
internet was
the vast majority of people who tried to
jump on the bandwagon in the late 1990s
so that was the general landscape where
john and i were located
and i don't work on my own uh um you
know if
nietzsche had got his dead on his grave
when he died i want to have the
individual that's dead on my grave
because i never believed in
individualism i think the idea
that we're sort of stuck in our heads
that descartes and the model can't love
this idea that we're stuck in our heads
so we can't really
you know connect with the outside world
well to begin with we do connect you
know with the rest of the world
including other human beings
we are incredibly social animals we're
tribal more
more than anything else and and i always
defend the right for humans to be human
i think try to change this into
something we're not it's always a
terrible idea
also very costly one so anyway this is
the late 1990s john and i meet because
i'm looking for a collaborator to work
with on writing the books
and i was offered to write a book on my
very radical
internet theory and i met john
we've had dinner this is an old store
now it's a well-known store and i use it
apparently i wasn't that good of a cook
according to john but i cooked some
chicken
it was in my house and we had a drawing
board in front of us
and we had the chicken and the drawing
board a glass of wine we love drinking
and we're sitting there and basically on
the map of the drawing board we had a
map of the book
of the theory and then john said
alexander
this is not just one book this is like
three books
this is like three books that we need to
write over the next 10 years
and i said okay i don't even want to
hear about the second and third book
right now i'm going to concentrate on
writing the first book
so yeah but john said just so that you
know that the theory is
white or way bigger than you've assumed
for just one book
but let's go into this and see who
you're right and that's how we invented
a whole new field of philosophy we
called vetturica
the veturica is essentially literature
that deals on future logical issues like
futurist issues
from a philosophical point of view say
you're going to do philosophy on the
future
not on the past not on the now you got
to do philosophy
on the future you do for tourica so the
vulgar version of a turkey day with
something like ray kurzweil and the
singularity theory
and the more advanced version of the
turka would be john cena christian
alexander park
so now you get the overall picture so we
started writing the first book was
called the nedocrats it's called the
nether cotton i think in german
um it became a worldwide success we
traveled around the world the next four
years with that book
two years later we started working on
the second book which is called the
global empire
and if the netocrats is quite accessible
i would say the global empire is
pretty hard technical philosophical work
but it's a very important book in
hindsight because it was with the global
empire second book
that we launched the entire
philosophical theory of how to
understand the current paradigm
and the title speaks volume because when
you hear the title the global empire
you think somebody's going to conquer
the rest of the planet say be
the cmp of china or believe it or not
bill clinton and some nukes from america
would conquer the rest of the world you
would have a global empire but actually
what we stated in the book this book
came out in 2003
was that the global empire already
exists it's just that if you don't take
the human perspective of the world we
actually
ask technology and you would discover
that the internet protocol
is already the constitution of an empire
except it's a technological empire
so now 20 years later it's probably
easier to understand that
you know ai would eventually create
individuals like agents
subjectivity the way human beings are
agents each one of us is an agent and we
can then have agency together we call it
a collective agency or tribal agency or
national agency whatever
but the agents that we human beings are
accustomed to when it comes to each
other we have conversations
it's an agency obviously a lot of
machines are going to have in the future
as well
and these agencies of them probably gone
at her
to give a global imperial order so
essentially what we said is that
as soon as you start to collect data
that data will want
sooner or later to have more data and it
will marry other
collections of data and the world's data
centers are very likely eventually
become
one huge data center this is something
we then explore
later in our work in our fourth book we
come to that but this was the global
empire
they wrote a very accessible book you
know to be
you know favorites among students and
you know people who want to get access
to philosophy
which is the one that i recommend for
you if you want to have an easy start
with a certificate
and this book is called the body
machines
and the body machines was essentially an
application
of our philosophy onto the individual or
individual human being
so if you want to write if you want to
read a book
on the digital age and what it means to
be a digital
citizen or a person in this age and how
it's different from previous paradigms
so what it means to be human
then the body machines is the place to
go
okay those three books were later you
know
re-released and repackaged as the
photorecord trilogy you can get the
entire photorecord
on amazon for example you can also read
those books separately but those are the
first three books
now we come to the current
second trilogy we're writing john
john demanded on me since we're turning
60 years old next year and this is going
to be the end of it
the the sixth book we're writing at the
moment after the deliberate is going to
be the end of it
because we're putting pretty hard work
into digital a bit on the
in the book before that which is the
synthesis book but these three books
are going to be eventually another
second trilogy and after that we're 60
years old we'll probably
resign and have our students write books
and kill their fathers and we have a lot
of drinks and we make
commentary on our work or something
that's the current plan
but the second trilogy which digital
libido is the central work
it's called the exodus so what we did
was that we started looking at fresh new
eyes on the current
contemporary society and looking into
the future and
then we discovered there's a lot more
that can be said about it that we
actually
discussed in the first three books
because the first three books our focus
is very much on the technology
we felt that philosophers had talked
about human beings quite a lot in the
past
they understood how human beings
operated we love hegel we love nietzsche
we love freud
we love all these thinkers who you know
talked and discussed human beings quite
a lot and on top of that we've got
psychonauts and psychology and other
things to try
and attempt to understand human beings
but we're also
deep ingrained in the world of
psychoanalysis which is where we get our
understanding of the human mind from in
our work
so we love slavishik for example we sort
of adapted to him
shot la khan before him and certainly
freud so we felt that
okay the second time around since people
now have
understood that technology is taking
over the world
on a radical new scale never seen before
even matching humans
even on the scale that we might not even
know whether humans will still be around
in the future
since everybody's figured that out and a
lot of people are writing poc books on
the topic like super intelligence by
nick bostrom and other swede by the way
or
you know people are doing all these
kinds of ray kurtz foul ideas of
singularity we found all these ideas to
be very naive
compared to what actually is confronting
us and not so much neither about the
technology
we're really named about what it means
to be human
so a key chapter digital libidos is the
chapter about the human constant
and the technological variable and this
is fundamental to
maya and john's philosophy is that if
you look at human beings over the last
200 000 years
very little has changed our brains are
about the same size they were 200 000
years ago
sorry but there's been no real
development to humans and the reason for
that is that even if you plan
to improve on ourselves and our genetic
equality
the problem is that we all get drunk and
the wrong person on a friday night
and then we breed and we have more
children and usually it's rather the
most stupid people are more children
than the smart ones
that's the bad news but that's the way
it works so at best
humans can be considered to be constant
but
humans can be studied much more deeply
than we've done in the past
and the reason for that is precisely
because of the human technological
interaction
what do you mean by that well we all
know by now
that we produce data
we all know that data is collected huge
data centers
most of these tech jobs are collecting
enormous amounts of data and they hardly
even know what they're going to do with
the data yet
okay but they figured out they're going
to be doing incredibly powerful things
with the data
if you use google maps or waste when you
drive you get an experience of what you
actually can start doing with people
once you get their data you know three
years ago you would go to say munich
and you would look for a restaurant and
you get 10 different suggestions usually
the 10 restaurants that were closest to
your ass
these days you get three suggestions
because google will have eliminated
seven of the suggestions
because they know that you're not going
to go there anyway because they know you
well enough and they know your budget
well enough
and you know the kind of taste you have
well enough that you would go to
those seven restaurants so they might as
well give you three but in reality
google probably already know which
restaurant you're gonna go to anyway
so they might as well book the table for
you and you go to that restaurant and
have a nice meal but they will also take
the profit from the restaurant in the
process
that's why tech giants will make tons of
money because they got the data
but if you ask a philosopher like myself
or john cena quest
what we want to do if we get access to
data we would love to do anthropology
so the discovery we had before we wrote
this new trilogy
is that we will actually know more about
human beings than
anybody has done before in history we
will not just have to sit and guess
like sigmund freud did successfully or
guests like mercia eliad did
successfully
guess like even jordan peterson or
cameron pogba down when they studied
you know the history of art or the
history of culture no we will know
because we will have data from history
on a level we've never seen before
that data will be collected and
processed on a level never seen before
so there's a whole new science now date
anthropology
and the data will not only be the sort
of data that you and i produce through
our
everyday behaviors which you can't give
it the data will also come from
the genetic makeup of human beings so we
will understand that there are different
men
and different women and things in
between men and women that exist in
human society
and we can start tracing the behavior in
a contemporary setting
and because we get the data from that
contemporary setting
we can then start applying it in human
history
and will be the first thing we do we
probably go
deeper into history to understand
ourselves
as historical beings that's exactly what
john and i set out to do
this is the foundation of the new
trilogy so
while we were experts on technology and
the relationship between man and
technology
when we started the neutrality we
started focusing more on man
using technology to understand human
beings
this is a philosophy we call
socio-analysis
and i think salvation should also call
his work social analysis rather than
psychoanalysis
just like psychology attempts to be a
social science
and sociology attempts to be social
science
psychoanalysis is an art form not a
and in the same way social analysis is
an art form
not a science since sociology tries to
scientifically
understand how human beings operate and
build their societies
therefore sociology we could instead do
social analysis
so that's the term we launched before we
started writing this trilogy it's like
well let's do social analysis what it
means to be human
and we realized that there were some
really you know cool
scientists out there who also saw the
data anthropology would be interesting
we even talked to google ideas they
realized that date anthropology would be
interesting for them
who wouldn't want to know how human
beings actually operate
especially in the social arena so
for example there's a whole new science
called social ontology
social ontology is the origin of the
human species as a social creature
this is the study the original nomadic
tribe
that apparently existed for some 60 to
70 000
years before human beings finally
decided to settle
and we only decided to settle some 8 000
years ago because some lazy woman who
was still
sexually attractive managed to sit down
her ass somewhere in mesopotamia and
decide she wanted to create the first
permanent settlement
and simply because with written language
around we could create the first
permanent settlement
that became the beginning of cattle
racing and eventually farming
and that's civilization as we know it
but before that fat woman sat down and
refused to move and people stayed with
her and were the first
nomadic tribe they decided to become a
settled community
before that happened some eight thousand
years ago we actually walked around for
at least sixty to seventy thousand years
and almost our entire genetic makeup was
shaped
during those sixty to seventy thousand
years
so if you understand human beings social
biologically
you understand how our genetic makeup
changed
during those 70 000 years to sort of fit
in
in some kind of tribal environment and
fit in with other human beings
we can orientate ourselves we'd have to
go back and actually do social ontology
which is just one way of application of
data anthropology
so this is what john and i set out to do
we started working with scientists
but we wanted to move into the
contemporary society we have today
so i'm going to cut it short about the
first book because it's a separate book
and it's now in translation to german
the first book is called
synthesism creating god in the internet
age
now why did we write a book on religion
and on god
the first thing we do because people
orientate themselves
according to some shared value
and the shared value is god in the sense
that if you allow yourself to think that
god doesn't necessarily have to exist
and god doesn't necessarily have to have
created the world or be outside of the
world
but god could be something that still
has to come then you would understand
that the way technology is used as human
beings over the past thousand years
is probably technology one day wanted to
take over the world
at least technology has developed and
progressed over the last 10 000 years
undeniably so in the last 100 years
undeniably so the last five to ten years
so technology is apparently moving
towards some kind of singularity
we could just call the singularity god
for analysis something we put in the
future
and this is a god that is still to be
created by us
or if the god of creativity like that
god is called syntheos theologically
speaking
so that explains how we wrote that book
first we laid the groundwork
we said metaphysics about the void it's
about the world it's unity the universe
it's about multiplicity
and it's also about what we can't create
in the future so we wrote that book it's
a foundational work
to prepare for digital libido and
eventually we're going to finish it all
off with the new narrative which is
going to be the third book the work at
the moment
but where does digital libido come into
the picture
well it comes into the picture because
we got to understand the paradigm shift
itself
but starting from a deeper understanding
of what it means to be human
so exactly the sort of chaos we're
seeing now
that's you know hit us so quickly post
corona europe and post corona america
for example
is what we talk about in the book so the
book is already prophetic only a couple
years after it was written
it's published in 2018 you can already
see many of these ideas in the book
are all over the place one of them is
for example wokeness
so the word woke did not exist you wrote
the book three years ago
it only came along the last year but we
write about what we call the rosso and
lynch mob and what we're saying
essentially is that
when there's no sense of direction to a
given society
meaning the future can only be chaotic
which is exactly the sort of society how
when you go through a dramatic paradigm
shift
because what happened is that all the
old power institutions collapse
politics is collapsing has become ironic
do you really care whether america
elects a cart member from south park or
a corona corps for president in november
probably not but the fact that those are
the two choices proves pretty much that
politics has become an ironic
social theory driven by dying mass media
we couldn't care less most of us so we
see that academia is falling apart
and at mass feeders falling apart and
they're all falling apart because woke
culture is now attacking them why is
vocal culture attacking these old
institutions that try to take over the
old institutions
simply because walk culture doesn't fit
in in the digital world
it's not the work people who win on
twitter
or when on instagram or when on facebook
why
because they do not provide us with the
value we as human beings are deeply
looking for
in any new medium we are confronted with
right what we wrote in the book called
the nidocrats 20 years ago
this is no longer a capitalist society
this is a potentialist society
this is all about who's wasting your
time the most valuable thing you have
now is your time
not your money that's why money is going
towards you know zero rates because it's
it's it's
cheap and easy to borrow money because
you cannot throw money into something
unless you sold it attention in an
attentionist manner before you saw
the capitalist matter so if you haven't
figured out how you're going to
communicate with the outside world
and figure out how they will bother to
listen to you when you do it you cannot
even be in a marketplace anymore
this is this phenomenon is called
tertialism and in the tensor society
the algorithms we have around us they
reward
us for giving quality to people
and for entertaining people this
principle is called the infotainment
principle
and all algorithms out there are built
on the infotainment principle so if you
keep the algorithm free
from interference the algorithm will
tell you
where you should go judging on your
previous behavior but also judging on
the behavioral people that you trust
not just your friends the people out
there who share interests with you
and if you are a lucky guy and if you're
a clever guy
people look for a quality that we call
antagony in our work
and taggity means you're so smart to
figure out if you just sit in an echo
chamber
and listen to the same people all day
long the same the same prejudices things
you've heard a thousand times before
and you're too comfortable in that
environment you're going to be a digital
underclass that we call the
conventariate
but if you go and look for people who
disagree with you
and challenge you that's how you grow
that's how you expand that's what
academia
used to be that's what mass media used
to be as a politics used to be that's
what any
great fruitful creative human
environment
is and that place today is the digital
realm
and if you're clever you get an
algorithm that will reflect your
behavior the behavior of others that you
trust the behavior of your friends
and you will suddenly discover that
people who have musical tastes that are
similar to yours but also challenge your
taste
suddenly you get tips on spotify what
you would listen to next and it's kind
of
wow i love this because by using the
algorithms i get directed to things
that i really want to consume or things
that i really want to get involved with
or interact with
or people that i want to talk to people
that i want to create networks with
but please note that the winners in this
game are the people who love the free
and open algorithm
we're adamant about this and did it
liberal we call these people libido
because in a sexual sense as you know in
german it's perfect because
gail in german a wonderful word that
should be exported to all languages but
guile is this part of
yeah i feel like i'm alive but at the
same time i'm also horny
english and american people are so
offended by sexuality that they trade to
pretend that these two things are
different things
we're adamant that we agree with the
germans nonsense deny
that actually being guided is a perfect
state to be in and we call it the
libidinal state that's why the book is
called
digital libido so it's a book about the
masters of this
age it's not that negative the title
itself says
everything it says that libido will make
you a winner in
algorithmic world and that's exactly
what the internet is
as in everything else being pulled into
the internet world
everything is now moving online rapidly
so
that means the people who can keep a
free and open algorithm and have the
credibility to do so will be the winners
so who gets the attention if you've got
a free and open algorithm who's the
winner
the guy provides you with the
infotainment value
that means infotainment information here
is educational
anybody who makes you feel you grew by
listening to them
anybody who educates you anybody who
provides more information
and knowledge and helps you make sense
of it which what good
teaching does good education does so
there's a great revival
for education here but it's going to be
all online and it's not going to have
any of these old institutional
requirements like
you have to sign up to university and
apply to course and go through testing
and certification
finally you know four years later you
get a little certificate that says that
oxford approved of you
those institutions are dead they're dead
and over because we can go online and
learn everything we do it the minute we
wake up we do it as soon as we have a
smartphone laptop in our house
because people love to get educated we
also love to get entertained
so if you can mix education
entertainment which is infotainment the
more you mix those two the more people
will come back to you
that will return again and again to your
website
they will listen to it more and more and
more and you will get the right people
not the most number of people not the
quantity
but the quality will get the right
people that you do want to network with
that you do want to collaborate with
they will come back to you
and because of your libido energy your
sexual libidinal
energy your pathetic energy in in in
this
this this notion that you want to be
human you want to collaborate with other
people you want to create collaborative
networks
and you want these networks to be
successful then you're a winner
now why then the really you know
drastic subtitles sex power and violence
in the network society
here's the here's the nasty story and
that's why this book is the dark one of
the three
because there's a lot of people out
there going to be losers
and they're also going to be online this
time that's the problem
everybody is online everybody has access
to smartphone laptop everybody in the
world is online
we're moving towards eight billion
people online and you'll you know
disqualify some babies and some corona
corpses and probably five billion people
are online already
so since the entire world now is the
internet itself is moving towards zero
cost
taxes and the entire world goes online
that means also that the losers will be
online
and the tragedy of all class societies
throughout history is that only minority
people are smart enough to become the
elite
and in this case it's not even elites
that have more money and wealth
than the underclass house this time it's
an elite that i only have one
one asset that they find very valuable
and it's their own time
and they don't want to hang out with the
losers they want to hang out with other
winners
so what happens if you think of the
internet first as a flat structure
everything is flat everybody has access
to internet everybody has a gmail
account everybody has a facebook account
everybody has a twitter account if they
want to you can open all these accounts
costs nothing you can you can you can
communicate with the outside world
at no cost at all that's a flat
structure of 5 billion people
but very very quickly you get some nodes
in this network you get some people who
have what
great infotainment value maybe a group
of people even have great infotainment
value
when this group of people have great
entertainment value they pull in other
people
after a while they're so attractive that
everybody wants to jump on board
and when that happens you got to
moderate you got to cut people out
it's called the network pyramid so you
get a network pyramid
hierarchy the hierarchy and contemporary
site is not between individuals
it is between the networks themselves
now
if you want to talk to peter thiel if
you're a tech guy or something like that
you don't have access to peter thiel why
because he has
a very tight schedule and he has many
many hurdles you have to go over
across to have access to him so he will
talk to you
okay that's very very hard now how do
you get access to the most powerful
people
in a world that is so nodal as the world
is becoming now that has so many nodes
and they're super nodes on top of the
nodes well
you can't you can't get through you
can't pay your way through
more than anything that's how we
disqualify the idea that this is a
capitalist power structure
and instead john and i say it's an
attentionless power structure
now so where will all the losers go but
what the losers
always did throughout history is that
they took whatever ideology they could
have from the past
that suited their interests and then
they went after the winners
and that's exactly what culture does
today
that's why it's a lynch mob it's the
exact opposite of an exodus
so the winners the digitally liberal
people
will create their own networks they will
then walk off with their networks and
make exodus
out of the society we have today i say
themselves in dealer realm
they might even isolate themselves in
physical realms they probably move to
city-states rather than
large big nations these days they move
to places like dubai and singapore
this even our plans and small republics
in europe like the czech republic in
estonia and slovenia
that maybe these small countries are the
places where the new elite will live in
the future
because they don't have to deal with
tons of and other people they don't
want to deal with
and since the vast majority of humanity
is no longer a
workforce that will make money for the
rich elite
that means we now have a problem of
redundancy
a lot of people and therefore they
therefore go for what nietzsche call the
culture
sentiment and and one of the chapters
did a little bit of it's at the end of
the book it's even called the dialectics
of our sentiment because it's a
dialectical process to the resentment
so you can read that chapter to deeply
understand how
we call the rossoil lynch mob is being
created
and what lynch mobs do
is that because they can never win the
argument when it comes to the substance
of the argument
they will attack you for the tonality
and the etiquette
they will attack you for your word use
they will say you must not use the
n-word and things like that
they will attack you for your etiquette
they will say you're rude and you're a
man or you're heterosexual or you have a
white skin color
whatever they happen to hate or whatever
is into hate this week right
so they objectify you they will tell you
must be deplatformed
they will tell you must be canceled you
must be taken off the internet
so you can no longer speak which
essentially is to kill you
because it's all life now happens online
then being the platform is nothing but a
digital execution
and they're doing all over the place and
they're using whatever platforms they
can
use to do that and those platforms are
exactly
the platforms that are dying so before
politics dies before academia dies
before mass media dies before old
industry dies this is about i'm talking
about marketing departments you know i'm
talking about pr
departments now at big companies they've
gone political now as well they're also
being politicized
so the wolf people are moving into all
of these different old institutions have
tried to milk whatever and just left
with them
why can they take over these old
institutions because
no necrocrats no winners in the society
none of the digitally liberal people
will be there
why because they're all online and what
are they doing online they're creating
social media accounts with hundreds of
thousands of followers
they creating new institutions like
parallax here where you can get
educated and entertained in the most
fruitful most interesting way
by people who put things on that site
they themselves would love to share
okay those are the winners some
increasingly see in autocracy rising
some people are focused on quality which
can be very smart you focus on few
people
but you reach people who will rise very
quickly through the hierarchy
or you focus on the quantity which is
fine too and then you basically mass
educate people how to become successful
online and get
hundreds of thousands of followers and
you know people will then follow you
because they realize that you use the
hashtags as a sort of guidance you
you give people a hashtag say wait a
second for example
when we talk about black people in
america
okay who's my favorite twitter account
candice owens okay
would i love candy zoe's to be the first
black president of the united states you
bet i would love candace owes to be the
first black president of the united
states
she is as anti-walk as she could
possibly get she's as nedocratic as she
could possibly be
she's strong she's powerful she's sexy
she's got she's smart like hell
she's funny like hell and she's deep all
the qualities that infotainment
says you should have and what about our
accounts they have
millions of followers already now she
reaches the masses in an autocratic way
other people focus on reaching just a
few people like we do to parallax but
these people are people who try to reach
and go into communication with
and then explore ideas together with so
you can do both
but that is being democratic meaning
we've left the old institutions
still being around open for the woke
people who show what we call the
consummatarian behavior
so what is your most important asset
then according to the libido
the free and open algorithm will it be
attacked
you bet it well you bet these resentful
people will try to attack your fee and
open algorithm
and they're already inside the google
and the facebook buildings and they try
to control you
how do they do that due to two ways
they do it through capitalism because we
said capitalism is dying it's becoming
redundant attentional system takes over
the world
what is capitalism doing then capitalism
tries to corrupt the algorithm
and it's called ads and at least google
separated the ads and we did google
search
we had the algorithm free and open so we
could go and search where we wanted to
search essentially we want the quality
stuff here
that potentialist algorithms are
fostering and throwing
throwing to us so we can find our way
through the chaos that's a phallic
order in the case it's called phallus
historically
fatigue ordering the case the algorithms
are very phallic so they would direct us
the ads were at least separate until
recently you had that separate
now google tries to put the ads at the
forefront so ever has paid for it now
gets
to block you and a lot of us have been
leaving and go to duckduckgo so it so
gets so disgusted with google search
because it's apparently becoming
commercialized
and we know that commercialism will
distort our view
will destroy the free and open algorithm
and there's a word we have for that we
call it spam
and we hate spam that's why having an ad
blocker today
and having a spam filter today is the
first freedom fight
that we see today in the internet
society that's digital liberal for you
now the other thing they try to do when
they don't have money and throw money at
things and try to desperately get your
eyeballs by paying their way to it
is that they try to manipulate you
politically
and that's how political manipulations
of world culture is about today
and this is what we write about due to
libido is bound to happen was that we
have a reaction
from a political resentful
group of people who who hate the
internet because the internet does not
work to their favor
because they simply haven't figured out
how to have a high infotainment value
they just don't have the talent for it
to be honest about it
all they do is that they got facebook
threads where they and moan and
grow
and that's what they did the entire
2010s for 10 years we had the trolls
everywhere
or the facebook threads everywhere and
the people then would get into these
environments create their own echo
chambers and they would look for an
object that they could go after an
abject is
what a lynch mob creates as an outside
they can run after and kill
to release the social tension within the
lens plot
hitler used it with the germans he
called it a jew
stalin used it with the russians he
called it the kulak
mao used it essentially and said that
you're going to go and kill your parent
because your parents are now become
objectified so they're abjects
so the abject is there all the time so
whenever somebody's being the platform
today
whenever somebody is being accused of
being politically inappropriate
and therefore should be culturally
counseled whenever the war culture does
that today
they do it with the same argument all
the time these people must be removed
and what they do is they objectify the
people that make them abject and they
can then attack them as much as they
like
and then release the social tension
after the object is finally the platform
but they will pretty much very soon
probably go after another object
because they're never pleased why
they're never pleased because they don't
get access to the power they're looking
for
ways to be attractive in the online
world all they can do is to use the old
platforms to attack you
so we're seeing a lot of this happening
today and digital libido explains it
now for example if you follow jordan
peterson
he's the pop version of the same idea he
experienced this very well i mean i
highly recommend you to read his books
maps of meaning was a fantastic worker
in the 90s
and he's writing these books about how
you're going to take these steps in
your life you know to take care of
yourself and to take some responsibility
to be proper grown-up
because you write about it digital
libido is that it's the infantilization
that is the major problem contemporary
society
an infantilized adult who's
not an adult who's not a proper man or a
woman who's just an infantalized boy or
a girl
in a grown-up man's or grown-up woman's
body
is becoming exactly the sort of crybaby
then becomes the central wall culture
so what what did the libido does is that
what jordan peterson has talked about
what camille paglas talked about in
america was douglas
murray talks about and writes
beautifully about this book the madness
of crowds
did it delivered as the more profound
philosophical work
that discusses the same thing and goes
to the depth and understands what what
are crowds
what kind of crowds are there okay there
are beautiful swarms when people
creatively collaborate but they're also
lynch mobs
and these mobs go after you and they
kill you and they're blood thirsty
now what is the difference between the
swarm of the mob and the swarm can
eventually lead to the exodus into the
new
whereas the mob will not want the new at
all rather the mob
was significant for the mob is that when
it has an accusation against you
the mob will tell you that you cannot
you can only repent
you cannot be forgiven so the lynch mob
will tell you that
oh here's an accusation there's no way
for you to actually argue against it
we call you racist or a bigot well how
do you argue against that
you can't okay so they go after you they
also say
there's no way out of the accusation
there's no end
date to the acquisition there's no way
for you to repay
the debt apparently you get because of
the accusation
so they will take any accusation they
want for example it can be that
women are fantastic men are nasty
that was me too essentially right so you
can make these accusations that cannot
be met you can't argue against them
but please remember these accusations
are apparently there to be valid for or
eternity so they're clearly there
to either milk you for the rest of your
life or to kill you
that's what the lunch mob wants with you
that what the linger wants to do with
you is either to milk you
or to kill you they have no interest in
you whatsoever
and being resurrected and getting back
up on your feet and eventually joining
them or whatever you know
and why would you join a lunchbox to
begin with why do you want to join a
bunch of losers right
you want to go and join the winners
don't you you want to be in the winners
club not the losers club
but we're already now seeing that
because we're all online
and we're seeing a small minority of
people who take on nether practical
qualities
and become the winners we explore this
in the later book explored in this book
too we have
the informationalists who replace the
old capitalists because they deal with
the information and data
we have the sensocrats to replace the
old politicians because
since socrates is now happening why
would you vote every four years when you
actually vote every second with your
smartphone
that opens up the whole area of
cinesocracy would that be a dictatorship
or could that be something more plural
and democratic
big questions to be answered we're
working with them for the next book and
we're involved in dialogues and those
issues
and also there's like a new digital
priesthood because
a group we love a lot john and i
probably because we belong to it
it's the group that we call the shamanic
cast and here's where it gets
interesting beyond a little bit
because we do social ontology because we
do date anthropology
because we know a lot more about humans
they've every day before
we also know history much better than we
did before we know big history
we know deep history we even know that
if we're going to look for the phallus
to direct us and give us order out of
the chaos
then the phallus also needs to be looked
for in history which we call the root of
the phallus
it's an expression that john and i use
so
we can look into history much deeper
than we did before and what do we
discover we do we discover a map
according to which people orientate
themselves
this whole new area of both philosophy
and science is something called tribal
mapping
so the travel map you see in digital
libido is a map you could put yourself
on that's where it gets personal in this
book so the travel map will consist of a
matriarchy at the center
which we call the inner circuit and it
would then have a patriarchy
outside called the outer circuit
so most men the vast majority men are
comfortable being regular heterosexual
guys you know
they want to do men's work and be proud
of being men and they want to work hard
and deliver to the women or whatever
that's what most men like to do like 92
percent of women like to do that
according to the data then we put them
in the outer circuit then the vast
majority of women are heterosexual women
and they love to work hard and
you know do the right thing in life but
they also love to give birth to children
will be part of the reproduction process
because they're part of the reproduction
process which is still the last time i
checked is the female monopoly
that means the inner circuit is the
center of the tribe because without the
inner circuit there can be no
reproduction and without the
reproduction the tribe cannot survive
so the fundamental idea of a tribe
something we call nomidology is the idea
that men need to serve women
so that women want to give birth to
babies if women don't want to give birth
to babies
society falls apart so there's a
matriarchal power which is the
negotiating power between the older
women
and the younger men who are horny on how
you negotiate the sexual ritual in the
tribe
now please note here though if they're
two border areas
we're talking about it there's first
euboria between the outer circle and the
inner circuit
that's when the androgynous cast lives
androgynous cast is about
four percent of the population according
to date of topology
there's four percent left though and
that will be called the shamanic caste
and the shamanic cast are outside the
outer circuit
they're basically walking back and forth
in between
tribes and many historians like jar
diamond
mercy eliad and others have done
anthropology on you know tribes in new
guinea and brazil they discovered
there are these people who put on weird
costumes and walk in and out in between
tribes even in the middle of
battlefields
shamans okay so the shamanoid
personalities are people who are not
very comfortable inside regular society
they're basically the outcasts
we probably pull most of our scapegoats
and people we want to you know
use as objects from that crowd too so
the shaman odds live a pretty hard and
rough life and take tons of risks
but they're the only go-betweens between
the tribes
now if you're the go-between between the
tribe and other tribes and
basically if you met someone from
another time you would kill them in an
instant right
because they'd be on your territory what
would they do there
if they weren't there to take your food
away from you or steal your wife or kill
you
you would kill them right not shamans
the shamanic people walk back and forth
between cultures
easily and are allowed to because
they're just a bit crazy aren't they
well if you have a monopoly on the
communication without the tribes
then you have a monopoly on the
communication with the outside world
that means it's not only the horizontal
that is monopoly
but also the vertical communication with
the outside world
that means religion starts with the
shamanic caste meaning you go to the
shaman
and have the shame and talk to the gods
and that's how you get a narrative and a
story for the entire tribe
now what we're doing in the book
essentially we're saying
this is a whole new field of expertise
we're basically philosophic
exploring travel mapping we're basically
telling you look if you like us have
access to google
ideas and their data google computers
around the world or data centers and
so you have access to tons of data the
first thing you'll probably do to find
out what it means to be human is you
would go
back to the origin of humanity going to
the 60 000 years of
nomadic tribes that shaped us you would
find a tribal map
and you would love to put yourself in
your specific male
or female or androgynous or shamanide
archetype
onto that map and here's the thing
we need to start separating these things
again we need to start separating men
and women
we need to start separating the
exclusively heterosexual people from the
very queer ones
we need to celebrate androgynous but not
as an ideal for the rest of society we
should
all not live like rock stars and die
young okay
a lot of the mistakes are made of the
20th century that jordan peterson also
addresses that we address more deeply in
this book
are due to the fact we weren't given a
proper travel map
so that each one of us could put
themselves on the map and said this is
the kind of man
or the kind of woman or the kind of
queer person or the kind of shaman
that i am and and this is you know
at the end of the delivery this is what
we want to provide and put forward
and just basically ask social scientists
why don't you dig
deeper into this because if you can get
a map like this for people
to to use as a map for themselves
throughout their lives
so much would be gained so i think i'm
going to finish there so uh
digital libido is at the center it's
very now now and now now because
obviously a lot of the things in the
book already happening
way quicker than we thought because of
corona that's already happening
we're seeing the move to digital is
happening much faster people expected
from digital we then go into an
augmented world where we fix
and mix digital and physical all the
time but we'll also see the old
institutions fall apart and they need to
be replaced
and before the old institutions that
used to run the world
but they no longer can because of the
internet but before
politics and academia and old industry
and mass media fall apart completely
there will be chaos
to get out of that case we need to
become enlightened and aware what's
going on
and we need to create new institutions
that replace
the old real symbolic and imaginary
powers that we were used to
but the only way to do that is not to
save the old institutions it's just like
you burned down versailles you created
the new institutions when you created
the republic in paris in 1789
it's the same thing all over again we
need to out of the internet
start talking to the people already
winners in the online world
from tech giants to twitter stars to
instagram stars whatever it is
and realize that these people are now
the power brokers they are the power
and we need to make them enlightened and
responsible
about the power they have but we also
need to
meet the current lynch mobs with
defiance
and the way you meet them with the fines
is you stand up against them and say
you're wrong and that's what jordan
peterson says that's what douglas murray
says
that's what alexander barney on
certificate say we say the same thing we
say that
whoever is the savior today ever is
brave enough and courageous enough to
stand up against the lynch mobs
doesn't solve the service and the way
you stand up the legion said listen
i'm against you but i'm not against you
because i'm not like you i'm not against
it against
i'm pro something and what i'm pro
is a return to original humanity i
understand how the collision between the
original humanity and digital can happen
what can come out of the digital tribes
can they then go from tribes to sort of
nations and empires that work in this
environment
working with that for the next book and
save and create larger social models
that people are comfortable with and
that people trust
and this is where crypto and all the new
other technologies come into the picture
to create much more advanced larger
societies
built on trust because otherwise we
can't save civilization
thank you a lot alexander
that was quite some dense
information on the lecture
um before i will open the
stage for audience members to ask a
question i
i wanted to just ask you about the
opinion of yours what
do you think there's a relation
between awokeness and his workness
culture
and uh a possible back backslash
in the political culture and favor of
trump
do you see there is a uh relation there
that people oh yeah yeah the problem is
this um what happened was that in the
1970s the left stopped reading karl marx
we use a lot of marks in our exotic list
and eyes so
for example netocrats a very marxist
book it's a book about class and class
analysis of contemporary society
but they stopped reading karl marx's
1970s because they were furious with the
workers that the workers didn't want the
revolution
so they went for something called
intersectionality starting in the 1980s
intersectionality was developed as the
new id
of the left but if you had asked marks
you would have hated it
because the idea was that you removed
class and pretended class did not exist
when in reality you should both have a
class analysis of the capitalist society
which is about money and wealth
and an attentionist class society class
analysis which
john and i have developed and the
tensions class analysis says that the
internet is
some people the small minority winners a
lot of people are losers and this is how
that works
okay so if you made the class analysis
you wouldn't need any of this worksheet
what happened was though that was
comfortable for the middle classes and
the you know
academic middle classes to sort of run
around with people of color and people
of
different genders and different
orientations and all kinds of exotic
shamanic looking people and pretend that
this was the future of the left
and i think there was a terrible
strategic mistake in the 1980s that the
left made both in europe and north
america
and here's how it works the way it works
is that you got to find an abdi because
if you're going to unify muslims and
women and homosexuals and everybody
whatever
and all kinds of new letters you haven't
even heard yet identities you must
remember apparently
probably like 78 different pronouns or
something but if this
this hysteria this this multiplicity
that no longer makes sense multiplicity
for the sake of multiplicity
they've got to be unified with something
so what the theorists like ernesto la
clau
and chantal moof and judith batler have
all said is that you got to find
something
that unites you and the unification is
no longer somebody within the group
it has to be from outside the group so
it's the same way that hitler founded
you you got to find an
abject it turned out it was very
comfortable for this alt
left since that existed first to
make the white heterosexual man the
abject
the problem is that the world has been
robbed of white's intersexual men for
the past at least 400 years
true but the vast majority white
heterosexual men happen to be regular
workers
not power brokers okay but you
comfortably put anybody with white
heterosexual
male in the category of what you could
attack as much as you liked
that meant the left turned against its
own history the left aggressively turned
against its own workers
those workers no longer found any
response at all in the left
which used to be marxist the usb pro
their interests
so they left where did they go of course
they then became the alt-right
but the problem with the old tribe is
just another roson lynch mob
john and i are not for trump or for
biden or for
woke or for anti-walk as things are now
or maybe we're anti-walk but
this is just more work so the other woke
here
or the awoke if you like in this case is
the alt-right so what did they say well
they say since this is now
nothing else than victimhood cults and
it's a competition for us the biggest
victim
and the biggest victim in this race gets
the biggest compensation
and nobody works any longer nobody's
creative any longer
nobody does anything constructive any
longer it's just a race to the bottom
of who's the biggest victim well if
everybody has turned against you
it's only a matter of time before the
white heterosexual man is gonna stand up
and said
no i'm the victim that is the alt-right
so we ended up in this trap with all
dragon gold left and i think the rest of
us sort of will pull back and retract
from it
and look at portland oregon in 2020
which we said several years ago that's
probably the first place we're going to
see an outright
struggle for months between the ultra
and north left where they're also going
to get weaponized and that's
exactly what's happening in america at
the moment so you see these two camps
the ultraviolet get weaponized and
it doesn't matter who wins the election
two months or not because whoever
loses at the losing side i'm sure are
gonna get weaponized and become more
military about what they do
and then we'll see if the national guard
of america and the next president can
stop them
because otherwise america would go
towards civil war
that's that would be my next question do
you see a civil war in the foreseeable
future within the united states
i did but here's where i have to bring
another friend of us thaddeus russell
and we did the podcast reason with that
is correct him he said no alexander
you're a
historian and whenever we've been close
to civil war of that magnitude the only
civil war america had was you know the
northern states against the southern
states it was essentially war about are
you going to have an industrial economy
or a farming economy in north america
and they then made slavery the symbolic
issue that struggled and that was a
civil war the northern states
won america hasn't had a new civil war
since then this was the mid eighteen
hundreds
but it could have another one and that
was my speculation with john cenacus i
said decreasing looks really bad
and because every time they alt left the
alt-right
they love each other because if they get
everybody else out of the way
this becomes a war between the two of
them that's what the old stuff are
trying to make joe biden
their candidate and they certainly got
kamala harris on board
so they can walk up against trump and
say listen even the election
who's going to be the president in the
white house is now nothing but all track
versus alt left
all other options are dead that's
exactly what these two
camps want they want a war between the
two of them and they don't mind because
they're better and resentful
and always which are bitter resentful
people have no problem at all taking two
weapons
it was exactly what the jacobins were
the pacifists at the beginning of the
french revolution it was exactly when
the jacobins
realized they were out of the power game
and they were losing the game that's
when they suddenly turned
blood thirsty and when the jacobins due
to the guillotine could take overpower
in france and ruled it for a few months
it was a bloodbath
i'd be very very careful with the small
culture today because
both the woke from the left and the walk
from the right
if they realize that they're beginning
to lose
whatever struggle they're involved with
and the way they will sense it is that
they will get less attention for what
they do
when they get less attention what they
do they will go more
militaric they will go more violent and
the violence will increase
now thaddeus russell says by that stage
when that happens
the old elite and the new elite say they
all the lead to washington dc and the
new elite of solid combat that would
unify
and create a national guard they will
just blow out these two camps
so america can return to peace i'm not
sure thaddeus is right though but at
least i'm listening to his arguments and
i think it's between
that is russell's intra-american
understanding and the understanding we
get from europe and we look at americans
like wait a second you had a civil war
in the past
over slavery you could certainly have a
civil war over woke this time around
unless we get some more civilized
positions now
that are neither of the two sides
all right perfect okay so now
um my reading glasses i can read also
the chat channel
right so we got a uh somebody who wrote
something
on the chat is there anybody else who
wants to address or
alexander or ask him something i think
it was a great
it's a good question but it's really
great from miranda
nogale so if mara wants to get involved
with us that'd be nice
okay the question is about the algorithm
i can i can i can read the question
so everybody uh also in the future will
be on board on that so i read it
people are mad or confused like hell and
dissatisfied
with the alternatives they are offered
by the elite how can algorithms help
people to understand
how we got here uh
and how the power system operates the
the elite would definitely resist like
health for its privileges
and all this is priced in in the
apocalypse
or singularity of all kinds waiting next
door or even in the abrahamic
uh as well as uh matsudaik or our uh
religions becoming a constant war with
each other since three thousand years
saying that what the hell is going on in
the heavens
that covers quite a lot of territory
there uh yeah i'm also very interested
in in the eastern perspective and we're
working a lot with that the new book
actually takes the silk route as a
starting point so
you're going to get a lot of there's a
raster and iranian heritage a lot of
indian and chinese philosophy in the
next book
that's for sure we don't start with the
greeks uh you some of it is already
digital libido so that answers that
but okay the interesting thing is that
how can algorithms help people to
understand how we got here
well you must understand that the only
way for the algorithms to operate
properly now is to not try to manipulate
them
because you once you get into the
manipulation game
you try to politicize the algorithms
like the others should be nudged in a
certain way because certain things are
desirable
you become the tyrant that's exactly
what authoritarian power does today
and this is the similarity between the
chinese communist party
and between woke activists in california
that's i'm terrified of what's going on
at the tech giants at the moment because
i know from inside google and facebook
there are a lot of people who want to
politicize that environment
and they want to redirect the algorithm
and it's happening already i mean if you
tap
marriage onto google search you
immediately get a black gay couple
like if you you you must not be racist
and you must not be anti-gay and
therefore they throw that picture into
your face even if your algorithm
wouldn't have done that if you had a
freedom open algorithm and
this is where we need to stay out of it
we need to just resist
infiltrating the algorithm so the
algorithm can stay free and open
and the way you you you explore that is
you basically ask people would you like
to have a free and open algorithm that
isn't manipulated by poli
people for political reasons and we
allowed her freeman open algorithm that
is cleanse the whole ad and spam
that advertises time to throw in there
would you like it to be without
manipulation corruption anybody would of
course answer yes i would like my free
and open algorithm to be free and open
now that means we must not use
algorithms in any way
we try to direct them we must let the
phallus rise
so to speak the phallus will
spontaneously rise
out of the system but if we for example
have a dialogue here
that is a quality dialogue both to us
and to people who follow it and
get engaged with it the algorithms will
point towards our dialogue if they're
kept free and open
because the algorithms will kill
everything that isn't quality out there
it will also sometimes kill some quality
to in the process that's so much quality
that most people don't even get it
that's tragedy trying to understand
there's a tragedy we sometimes have to
live with
but essentially if you do quality stuff
these days and you're good at explaining
it to people and hopefully do so in a
fun way
you will get the algorithms to go your
way anyway
and that's the way we should look at
algorithms stay out of manipulation
okay now we um have another question
from roberto he asked what good reasons
do we have to suppose that we can
now have a real comprehension of humans
many ages have had this illusion
i don't think it's only a matter about
data of data about humans
no that's correct very good question
okay but we know more
we will know more now whether we know
more insider enhancing and processes
it's a different question
okay for example when i study philosophy
and when i sit with hegel and nietzsche
i discover that they spent every day of
their lives reading tons of books much
more than i
do and i discovered that my students
that are say 25 years old that i work
with
read far less than i had done when i was
25. what terrifies me is that we spend
too much time surfing and jumping from
one thing to the next and
we learn a few lines that are good for
cocktail conversations we actually don't
go deep
but human beings are dialectical there
are also responses to things that we do
we no longer want to be
in the facebook threads behaving like
trolls that belongs to the 2010s we no
longer want to stay in echo chambers we
want to be challenged we want to be
antagonic in our behavior
we're learning as we go along and the
same thing here that
i hope that people go in and stay within
deep studies i actually think that
monasteries will come back in a big way
but the monasteries will be wi-fi
miners just turn around so they can both
be digital or physical but i think
people will have
enormous need to isolate themselves
maybe for months at a time
to really be able to study something
deeply without getting disturbed
that's one of the lessons we'll learn
from the 2010s and whether where the
hell can i be for four months to study
something properly
without constantly being disturbed by my
smartphone and
these are the things people are learning
and we can call this a digital monastery
culture
i would prophesize and say that's
definitely gonna come in the next 10
years
but when it comes to the data because we
have more data available
about humans human genome the human body
the human history the human brain how it
operates and how it interacts with the
outside world
we can at least theoretically say that
we will probably
be able to say a lot more about humans
and humanness than we could in the past
right okay so now um i just see that
i can't integrate the participants in
this life
zoom so we have to do it via chat
there was a question by jonathan i read
it again
can you say more about your
understanding
of the difference between drive desire
and transcendence
how do you relate these psychoanalytic
concepts in your social analysis
thanks great question love that one
jonathan okay
so um john cena crystal has found that
chocolate con's division between drive
and desire
left a little too much to the
imagination so if you're going to talk
about drives
and a division of drives then uh lacan's
description of drive is something
mechanic so it's a mechanic something
demandingly
mechanic is a good way to describe your
drive so what is mechanistic about it is
drive
and desire is always that's something
that's exclusive for humans
animals don't show desire and and desire
is here
uh something that comes as a byproduct
of language so
you we symbolically desire something and
we have an imagination about the drive
okay although i think makon is ignoring
instinct a bit too much here because a
lot of human behavior is just pure
instinct say for example you know when
you're born
if you drop the baby on the mother's
body you'll immediately crawl to the tip
and start sucking the tip
out of instinct and instinctive of
course how animals
intelligent animals maybe operate so it
makes sense to speak about
instinct and the great thing with
instinct is we then get a name for what
we can call animalistic drive
and it helps people to differentiate in
psychonauts between be mechanical in the
drive and animalistic so
the animal in me did this is what we
would talk about in terms of instinct
and
the mechanic side of me the eerie weird
thing in me that is just strictly
mechanic that's just
energy being thrown into some kind of a
system and then it does things
is what we then call pure drive and pure
drive
and instinct then has desire correctly
which is what we get from the symbolic
and we get that from language
but what's interesting here is that we
also need to understand transcendence as
a drive
what do you mean by that well the idea
that
you can be part of something bigger or
greater than yourself
is a drive the idea that even if you're
gonna die one day
you can leave a heritage behind like
your children and they can have a
different world than yours and you can
actually prioritize
what's great for your children you can
prioritize in your life
what's going to happen long after you're
dead rather than just prioritize your
own self-interest
that's transcendence transcendence is
incredibly important for human beings
simply because it comes out of getting
tired of the desire
and it also comes out of the fact that
we're tribal creatures
and the the way we came up with
transcendence that's different from
desire was that
you know it's always when you go back to
your masters
and you discover there's a loophole in
their argument
so you become more them than they are
you become more freudian than freud
that's what you discover where freud
misses out on things
you become more hegelian than hegel
that's where you discover the zeitgeist
must be split it can't be one
you can be more nietzsche nietzsche
discover the ubermesh must have company
he's a tribal creature so there must be
at least two
okay so you discover these guys have it
really figured out fully and you use
them against them you can do the same
with lakhan
and ninja's name is shot khan is he
never discusses like he wouldn't do
because he likes to be dark and negative
and everything like he's he's very much
a gothic guy let's put it that way it's
a bit like lovecraft right
solacan never discussed in his work
what would it be like to be his
analysion you know his patient
and be successful with the process what
does it mean to be
somebody who's post psych analysis
because this obvious statement when you
post psychonauts lacan himself hopefully
personified that state
even if you arrive in a sort of weird
eerie lacanian place we realize that
you're trying to fill your empty self
all the time
you can't stop doing it even you know
it's kind of in vain okay
even if you do that there is an
enlightenment to knowing that
and the answer we have is that if you
get the enlightenment the laconia
enlightenment which he doesn't discuss
then that state is what we call
transcendence
so we have four different drives and i
think it's a richer variety it makes
sense to add more to it without
inflation
to speak about instinct pure drive
desire and transcendence when you
approach human drives
right okay now
we have a question for from aurelion
um i will read it again also i mean
i came to this book the digital libido
after first reading a lot of nietzsche
when i've read when i read nietzsche i
found on him something which
something which just seems solely
lacking today and which almost seems
incompatible with the climate of today
and i find in you
and a few others that you've mentioned
your approach to philosophy and politics
and of course in your book
well okay what is it
what it is is the willingness to speak
the harsh harsh truth
to critique us everyone the dominant
culture
and the cultural expressions of the time
and uh and
analyze its true consequences why do you
think this type of truth speaking
and critique so incompatible with
today's
why ah okay why do you think this type
of truth speaking and critique
is so incompatible with today's cultural
climate
is it also part of the infantilization
of academia and society
in general very good question
so um aurelian the yes uh
the infantilization is partly
responsible for that the infantilization
according to us
is we agree with nick lund started in
1945.
um we had hitler we had stalin we have
we call fake
phalluses in this book and we're looking
for the authentic father the authentic
leader
even more so we're looking for the
authentic savior to get us out of a mess
the order in the chaos you know and um
when we get the dictators today that
will be xi and ping for example who
don't get it and therefore our fake
phalluses and can take us into you know
terrible states i think china is a very
unstable culture today because of the
communist party's current dictatorship
and those fake fallacies are really
dangerous and often what they do turns
out to be bloody because they personify
the same mechanisms that we see woke
they personified the lynch mob their
tyrants
but why is this rare well it is
corruption and
this is also because it's easy for us as
human beings to see things
short term so we watch the news every
day we get up and watch the news we
react to the news
but what we what we don't see we don't
see the long
term movements over long periods of time
along the way
as our rigorous song calls it
beautifully and we do that then we see
patterns for example the corruption of
academia
was very much down to the simple fact
that if a professor disagreed with
another professor none of them was fired
you see so it's not like you competed
for the same post there wasn't any
competition like there is in the
marketplace
at least the marketplace or say a bazaar
historical marketplace
there's a certain point because new
forces come into the marketplace all the
time and want to market their worst
therefore there's competition because
there's competition you keep a fresh
blood in the system
but the way i could deem this worked
over the last say 60 to 70 years
is basically that oh okay so these two
different fields do not agree with each
other let's put a new prefix in front of
them invent even further institutions
so we had a massive inflation of
academic production
but the quality was lower and lower and
lower why
because there was no antagonism thrown
into the system
there were no challenges thrown into the
system and if you're never
challenged in what you do you keep
producing it and producing it and
producing it
and it becomes more and more junky and
finally nobody cares about it it's like
an academic paper today does anybody
care to read it no
nobody reads academic papers any longer
do academicians care
they haven't seen this movement because
it's taken decades for them to reach
there
they get paid more than ever because we
force the students to take on academic
educations they no longer need
so this is like it's like one huge
institution that's about to fall
dramatically in the next 10 years and
that's academia
simply because why would anybody pay for
harvard university now
in the fall of 2020 when everything at
harvard goes online and it costs you 55
to attend a semester at harvard where
you can get the same thing at praxis.com
for twelve hundred dollars
with a certificate it's only question of
time before the certificate from
praxis.com looks better than the one
from harwood because practice.com is not
completely rotten
with woke culture like harvard is so
harvard is killing itself from all
different directions at the same time
and of course if harvard does that you
can never imagine how bad it is at the
smaller universities and colleges in
north america and asia and europe at the
moment so
we're seeing this lowered quality
everywhere
as a lowered quality and people need to
keep their day jobs and they need to pay
their mortgage
and when people have loans to pay and
anybody who's below 50 years of age in
our society is loans to pay
and everybody's above 50 years of age
when they're no longer corrupt
have money to spend and then they don't
care any longer that means the people
who do the careers now between 25 50
years of age have more
gifts to pay they need to keep their day
jobs they often have the day jobs with
these old institutions they're dying
and therefore they keep their mouths
shut it's a massive
corruption of the whole system and i get
it here in sweden because when i speak
the truth here because i've basically
managed to build the position from which
i can speak
my mind i'm paid to do it and i'm unique
in that sense
when i meet people they'll say well you
can't say that the things you say
and now you say well i just did yeah you
can say that
yeah because i created a platform from
which i can be
courageous to be courageous basically
simply being smart
about creating a platform for which you
can speak freely
and that to me today is to go online
create your own channel if you don't
trust
youtube create your own web page or
something or go to some more open
service get a garden parlor account if
you don't touch
twitter but the way place to go right
now is to go online like parallax is
done here you go online you do
everything you do online
and suddenly you created the free and
open platform which is also free and
open
for you as an agent to act from
so i think i think the problem with the
dominant culture you're talking about
correctly aurelion is this all this
dominant culture comes from
the old institutions and i think it is
impossible to speak the truth like
nietzsche did it's impossible to speak
the truth
from within politics it's impossible to
speak the truth from within academia
it's impossible to speak the truth from
within mass media and it's impossible to
speak the truth within old industry
but if you leave all those and move to
the digital realm
then it's possible to speak the truth
nietzsche would agree strongly
perfect we have two more questions one
by our own andrew sweeney he writes
treble tribal mapping is about
discovering archetypal identities
if is this how we solve victimology
that is the victim being ultimate
identity of the post-christian
nihilistic
modernist ethos by giving people
primordial identities by rediscovering
the primordial identities how we do
how do we not reproduce the scapegoat
cycle
between eternalism nihilism
god victim etc okay
good question now good question uh
travel mapping helps at least
for people to orientate themselves in a
timeless manner
before they put themselves into
something very temporal which is the
digital world we live in now
so we want to help people to do that
this is also a new ology this is
archetypology so archetypology
especially the science when you decide
what kind of personality are you
now there's a problem though i can
guarantee you
that if you apply archetypology on a
timeless manner you will end up with the
sausage and the 60 000 years to shape
those
that means i can guarantee i can talk to
any man or woman alive today and say
you're a winner
in the sense that we had a job for you
or a social position for you
that would not make you resentful but
actually make you proud of who you were
in the original tribe but because
society is so different today
we can't guarantee that's the case now
that that is the tragedy of history is
that
we can guarantee the people had a
position because they genetically are
here and they were given birth to by
somebody who wanted them to be alive
hopefully
and because of that the archetypology we
can give this to give them okay
5 000 years ago you would very surely be
given this
opportunity to do this this is the type
of personality you have
this is the archetype you belong to but
because that archetypology also has to
be contemporary one for example when it
comes to education your profession your
career
what kind of man or woman or queer
person you want to be
the problem here is that we don't know
that and we don't know where those
people are going to end up
and the people who then become the
losers i think we have to be honest
enough to say you have a personal
type that finds it very very hard to
make a korean good jumper society
and because we're going to put a lot of
robots in the factors and not guys like
you because the robots work better than
you do
um my god what are we going to do with
you okay we don't have that answer and
of course
of course people who are left outside of
systems like this you know
the lump and probably territor karl marx
would call them because they're not part
of the winning proletariat
they're part of the lump and prototype
for which karl marx had no hope
so we're going to have a sort of
technological lump and proletariat and
of course they're going to be
recruitment ground
for people who are better and resentful
and the only mode they know because they
cannot commit an exodus
they can can't do exodus is they're
going to recommend you join one of the
lynch mobs
and if you're alive you're around we're
going to see more lynch mobs
we don't have any guarantee that's not
going to happen it's actually very
likely
all we can do is that we have to argue
against these lunch mobs
we probably have to leave and end up in
an atomic bomb bunker in
new zealand or move to slovenia or
somewhere we get lower taxes now
protected
and our borders protected i think gated
communities are going to be all over the
place digital liberal says that gate
place because the elite we want them
so uh it's it's not it's not an easy
picture at all when you look at the
overall picture but
you know is the recruitment ground here
for
cults over a sentiment yes there is
would these calls be powerful
they will not be attentionalistically
powerful but as soon as they get
some kind of attention especially taking
over all the situations distiller around
they're bound to do so so expect the
mess to stay for at least another 50
years
right okay so now i have let me just
see um
one question by jonathan
we had a question about time also yeah
and yeah and by carl and so we started
yeah
i think they're connected because
they're both time questions right yeah
okay so
just answer to carl let me read the
question
so future listeners know what you're
referring to right
so the question by carl is what is your
take on circular time
right so uh the next book we're working
on the follow-up today libido is called
process and event
and this is the very likely the title of
the book as well if it said we did a
little bit of where they connect is that
data libido discusses the original
nomadic tribe
and it then discusses its idea of the
world which is called nomidology because
it's a nomadic tribe it's on the move
so everything has to be about how you
move a tribe
well it's led by phallic power split
phallus
priest and chieftain always split they
lead and then a match arc at the very
end who pushes you forward
this is the mythology for example moses
aaron and miriam the three siblings that
lead
the hebrews out of egypt so it's it's a
mechanism that returns in
in exodus now that's that's how the
original nomadic tribe moved
uh they believed in circular time
mercedes showed this in his 1950s book
the
if you read the book shamanism for
example a mercedes
another book is called the eternal myth
the the myth of the eternal return
you read mercy elliot a great romanian
anthropologist from the 1950s great
inspiration for jordan peterson by the
way it's his biggest hero
and you read eliad you'll discover that
the patterns he discusses are always
about circular time and the opposite
circle of times we talk about it is
linear time and linear time is quite
recent
that innovation was less than four
thousand years old it was invented by
zoroaster who founded zoroastrianism in
persia asian persia
and it basically said that okay because
not every circle of history is the same
there is a small deviation and the
deviation can actually be expanded on
for example the sun can build the
societies different than the father did
and because written language had arrived
it became obvious
that there was more data available even
more data available you can create a
more advanced culture
so so raster's idea was simply that
because we could create a more advanced
culture
it doesn't make sense to think of time
as something circular
so introduce the idea of linear time and
the linear time
is called eventology that's what the
book is called process and event it
discusses process time which is circular
time
and it discusses linear time which is
eventology
and these two different ways of looking
at time or action also moving into time
studies per se
because if you study subphysics which is
like the part what's prior to physics
because it looks like a universe is a
big bounce in order to be banned
you discover that physicists need two
tone dimensions for that to work
and funny enough time as we know it
turns out to be linear it started
13.8 billion years ago with the
expansion of classic space time with
expansion of the universe that's
guaranteed
but there must be time prior to time
it's called hypertime and it turns out
hypertime is very warped and weird maybe
not circular
but incredibly warped and weird so we
don't end up with infinitives we look at
different universes
now that's an area of study that i love
it's an area of study where physicists
and philosophers and just everybody is
really interested in grand theoret going
at the moment
but i find it very very interesting that
actually linear time and circular time
are returning
in the world of physics as well today
so we had jonathan had another great
comment about time right but
again let me read it for future
listeners so everybody's on board
jonathan asked if there is time i have
one more
question throughout your books you use
the term network
dynamical can you say more about what
you're referring to with this term
particularly in a social context rather
than in cosmological context
thanks yes i am a radical relationalist
and so is general cynicist what we mean
by that is that
relations are prior to relotta so before
you get interested in the object that
little ammonium comet is sitting staring
at as the subject
there is there are relations there
there's the relation between the subject
and the object there's also relation
within the object
so everything starts with relations and
fundamentally that's what physics is
physics is the beginning of relations
that are sub-physical
so potentialities become probabilities
that they become
actualities and once something is
actually you can start measuring it and
you can bump into it and be walled at
anything
so relations are prior to a lot in our
philosophy we're
radical relational relationalists and we
take a lot of this work from alfred
north
whitehead who was the originator of
radical relationalism so
he took leibniz's and nietzsche's ideas
of relativism
and basically said it's not only that
the relations between the objects
are relative but actually the objects
themselves are relative within
themselves
so he's like he's like you know an
inverted hegelian in that sense
he thinks like hegel but he thinks i
can't go about objects and subjects
and when you tear the objects apart that
way you discover they're just relations
or relations and relations you become a
radical relationalist
now that is cosmologically correct but
why would we reply to human beings
because human beings are tribal
creatures now
if i wrote philosophy for polar bears
who are very solitary animals
they hardly even get along they even eat
their own kids if they have to like they
they're not like you know they're not
sentimental as humans are when it comes
to being brutal
so polar bears are solitary animals if i
wrote philosophy for polar bears in
relation to technology
i would probably write to them why don't
you explore individualism it's a
beautiful idea for all tests among
humans and actually makes sense for all
polar bears
okay the vast majority of human beings
are fortunate not autistic or
narcissistic maybe i am to a certain
extent but you know
not more than i can be social creature
human beings are deeply
tribal social creatures so to understand
human beings it makes sense
actually to apply relationalism onto
human beings
and in the synthesis and book we explore
this idea we dig deeper into individual
libido and we call it
social relationalism so social relations
is the philosophy then when we apply it
on the
man technology interactions we call it
network dynamical
because networks are dynamical in
themselves
but between networks there also has to
be certain dynamism
and if a network is no longer dynamical
it tends to die
we lose interest in it and we leave it
and we get out so that's why network
dynamical which term using all our work
is now tied also with social relations
all right another question
by aurelian i hope i pronounced that
correctly
uh is that a female name i don't know
aurelion i guess so is it a male name
i'm a phd student myself at malmo
university
studying philosophy but you're saying
universities are becoming obsolete
and your prophecies all seem to come
true so any advice for an aspiring
philosopher
philosophy is so important but i don't
see other platforms
for it outside academia where does
where does philosophy go in your opinion
ah and he
says he is male so there we go okay uh
so
really uh john cena kissed and i knew
that this would happen already we
started working together almost 25 years
ago
so we are academics uh but when i do
academia for example stop on school
economics i'm actually teacher at the
management
on the management level digital studies
department at
the management so that's executive
education essentially i teach people who
really have careers
middle aged and they want to move from
middle management to top management
within corporations and institutions
and they want to know what's going on in
the digital world and i teach them that
but i'm actually not there as a
philosopher i knew philosophy
would lose by being inside academia i
had the discussion with two friends of
mine you might know
alexander brady island was a very
talented young danish philosopher
and cattle last is a great new canadian
philosopher who
who works in the tradition of lacan and
shishek and he's based in london
and we had a conversation a private zoom
conversation today and we talked about
it
and i said maybe speculative realism
which was
very very hyped like 10 years ago with
graham harman and quentin melissa and
you know some other guys not much
happened whether to be honest about it
not much came out of it
maybe that was just the last hype coming
of out of academic philosophy these were
all academic guys made
academic careers and the way they
pursued their philosophy was by writing
books in response to one another
and then sitting in white-walled art
galleries
having philosophy discussions with black
turtlenecks so it's
always become like a parody of what it
means to be a philosopher to do that
kind of work
i never wanted to be part of that scene
i i opted out
i knew i had to find my audience and the
people i wanted to collaborate with
in a you know much longer route going
outside of academia to find them
but i'm now discovering when we reach
2020 and
johnson my books are just about
everywhere and get to travel around the
world and we have a fantastic life
filled with cognac and cigars and great
books and you know great discussions and
fantastic students and
and fantastic interlocutors exactly the
life we wanted we finally can live
without but we took the outside of
academia
i would strongly recommend you to find
other friends your own age
and then build your own digital
monastery and keep it digital for now
and have regular soon conversations and
other things and then work on your
philosophy
and then we won't express your
philosophy also remember
i think jordan hall said this to me last
year in america as jordan hall said
i intend to be the first philosophers
and socrates to doesn't write books
and see if he can do his philosophy
strictly through using podcasts of
webcasts and new media
that that's a big challenge because
actually at the end of the day it's
great to write a book and summarize your
work at least somewhere
that's why you put the books out there
if you're a philosopher but i would
strongly recommend you to self-publish
your work i would strongly recommend you
to leave academia as soon as you
possibly can
i strongly recommend you read as much as
you possibly can get as deep into
philosophy as you can
and express your own way of doing it
like find yourself on the bigger tribal
map of philosophers
what exactly is it that you could pursue
and philosophize on and then write about
and express
and then do it from a digital physical
monastery platform
parallax here good example much better
than investing academia today
right now we have a question by
oliver grebel uh oliver grebel is a
philosopher
uh and a very smart one indeed he
translated
synthesism you know which comes out uh
in the spring of next
next year and so he writes hi alexander
and tom and everybody great to see
alexander giving a lecture
i've actually translated one of your
books from the english translation
having become quite uh acquainted with
some of your ideas i
look look forward to see you interact
with other postmodern thinkers
in the german integral conference which
is now cancelled
my question do you know the integral and
cultural evolution
teachings based on gene gapsas and
claire graves work
there's notably the idea of an
integration of traditional
modernist and green post-modern cultures
mitigating culture wars
at least in major western nations do you
believe
at all in an integral culture which
could reconcile
these clashing cultures from what i've
just heard from you you seem to see
the groups elsewhere sociologically and
culturally
natocracy consumptariat etc
so i'm very happy actually that uh that
he asked that so
um go ahead very good question actually
there are a couple of questions in there
yes i am very familiar with gibson
graves work and i deeply prove it i
think it's great
i i you know i'm an old fan of ken
wilber at least as a psychologist i
think it's brilliant and i think it's
very useful
but when it comes to the philosophy
itself this
eagerness for integration sometimes
tries to jump to the integration and
doesn't realize that you always pay a
price when you do that
uh to begin with traditional modernist
and green post modern cultures here
are very much from the old paradigm for
example um
when it comes to the green issues that
are very adamant you know they need to
be solved we've got climate change ahead
of us
i'm much more echotopian than i'm an
environmentalist because the
environmentalism ended up as sort of a
dystopian cult
headed by a young swedish clever girl
called grand the timber
but that doesn't solve the issues the
way to solve this is develop new
technologies
that actually solve the issues it sounds
kind of weird to use technologies
against something that partly blame
technology for
but i think a culture of exploitation
can be replaced with the culture of
implotation
that's something we worked on in the
nethercrafts 20 years ago once you
understand the principle implotation
you then have implotation within systems
from anything you build say algorithms
anything else use implotation
as a principle the system in itself must
be sustainable you build the system in
such a way
that if the system is still around
around 100 years from now you built it
the right way
okay so implotation can be used as a
principle then you discover that with
equitopianism
and maybe fourth generation nuclear
power which environmentalists in europe
are aggressively against because they go
for wind and solar power or whatever
they also hate genetically modified
foods or maybe genetically modified
foods in 2030 it's not the same thing
that it was in 1992.
so you cannot just ban future
technologies outright because you're
scared of them
that's a dystopian attitude you need a
utopian or even a better a protopin
more playful attitude towards technology
and that's from an echotopium
and equitopianism is an idea that grew
out of the digital environment
it didn't come from out of an attempt to
integrate environmentalism with its
opponents which
essentially climate change deniers
rather environmentalism
ended up debating the climate change
deniers endlessly
because environmentalism itself had
become too authoritarian
now the second you stopping in
authoritarian allow for difference
rather than integration allow for more
difference rather than less within a
field of study
you discover that actually you silence
your opponents and it's actually your
side that wins the game but it wins the
game by actually moving on
to a new higher dialectical level
that is to really understand hegelian
dialectics and that's what's lacking i
think in wolvers analysis
and i think my response to that is that
i don't want the integration if the
integration is only in integration of
several old movements that haven't even
sorted out yet whether they have a
heroic
or a victimhood focused attitude towards
the future
because i can assure you if you're going
to build the future
and make that work and save us from
climate change
and save us from the atomic bomb
spreading across the planet and causing
havoc
we're going to solve the major problems
of humanity and the solutions those
problems are kutopianism cosmopolitan
some other ideas that we explore in our
books
the only way to do it is actually not to
integrate the old
fields of study too early but actually
partly to leave them
move into new deals of the realm then
discover who represents
heroic here and not heroic in a naive
super comic book figure sense because
that's dangerous right
but you know truly phallic in the sense
that we're gonna get there
we're gonna make the exodus we're gonna
achieve this and this is how we're gonna
do it
and we're gonna implement certain
principles that shows that we've learned
from history
and we're not going to repeat the
mistakes the previous paradigm we're not
going to exploit the planet to death
we're going to
employ every resource we have you know
once you implement those ideas you learn
from history
use new technologies you're more data
available the chance of you succeeding
where the previous paradigm
failed increased dramatically
and that to me is not about integrating
too quickly it's all it's all about
keeping the space more open to more
lively debate
and please stop d platforming and stop
council culture instantly
and the reason why the integral
conference in germany was cancelled was
because there was a deep platforming
activity that went on
and woke us found its way into balbarian
culture
i could tell you that will be in culture
is a really dangerous place you don't
want to be there
well yeah that that was the debacle as
you say in
germany in regard of the
integral conference because the person
in question if i may say so
uh were you of course and so it was just
it is like the the spirit of debate
and discourse which should be like the
prerogative
of an integral community was hijacked by
a woke actor and woke uh agent
who doesn't jive really with what you're
saying but in a way
wasn't fit to debate you actually
although this option was on the table
but he flat out declined
and so you see where where the wind was
blowing from
you know so that's what i don't do i
debate with everybody
at all times and you know as long as i'm
being treated with respect to people
into some dialogue i can debate with
anybody
that's called democracy something we
should be proud of we created in the
previous paradigm we're now
trying to save and construct a new
version of it that actually works in
digital realm we haven't really figured
that out yet but i think uh
a system of plurality because plurality
is good in itself plurality is good for
creativity
and says we need to be pro-topian in the
future you know not reach for utopia
british or protopias kevin kelly calls
it
and i think the protopin ideas could
foster a sense of plurals and socrates
the model for the future
we're working on it it's not easy you
know but we we all the chilean pings of
the world an answer
we all the fake fellas of the world
answer what authentic phallic power
could look like in the digital age
and it's gonna take us a while to get
there but that's the real challenge
okay we have two more questions so
or three again um so i start with
anton you talk a lot about different
archetypes
in the tribe you often mentioned the
trickster
what other archetypes are there and what
roles do you think they play
in modern society very good question and
very good question in the sense that i
will not
answer to it fully uh we are not
anthropologists and we don't pretend we
are so we do philosophically speaking as
we launch the tribal mapping model and
says this is a better
model to understand human beings than
going to individual psychology which
makes no sense at all that's why
psychologists failed
there are psychologists to realize this
greg enriquez and america and some other
psychologists doing great work at the
moment and
trying to revolutionize psychology
because he got stuck in the individual's
paradigm where human beings should not
be in the first place
so travel mapping helps it also helps to
sort out why
the shamanic castes suddenly became rock
stars and idols in a culture that had no
other men especially or proper women to
look up to
we were missing the patriarchs and the
matriarchs in a youth worshiping culture
and what we learned from the 20th
century is that when you go for youth
worship instead of
wisdom worship which is incredibly rare
in history and
very dangerous when you start worshiping
youth you tend to worship youth when
they behave in a shamanic or androgynous
manner
that's not for everybody the thing with
androgynous cast that i celebrated but
just like camille pogba said that
yeah but androgynous characters are
meant to be a minority and they're meant
to be the go between between men and
women and we need them precisely for
that reason
and that's also where they're
comfortable in any culture so i think
getting the tribal map right is what we
work with
and i think it's up then to
anthropologists and archetypologists
to find the exact archetypes for people
to identify with
but that's deeper social scientific work
that not necessarily philosophers should
undertake all right
i think we have a last question now from
miran it reads since the techno
uh since the technologic imperative is a
driving force
and technology is highly militarized and
used as tool for conquering
and control especially in a faustic in a
fausti culture
who could control the technicians will
technicians hire
their own priesthood holding them away
from what you call
the barrett absolute yeah it's the the
borrowed abstract it's actually constant
it's not in the digital limited block
we're exploring it for the next book
so um the problem is whenever you ask
somebody to control somebody else you're
gonna go for authoritarianism in two
seconds because otherwise how would they
be controlled i don't think we can
control the military through elections
we've learned that because that's what
it falls apart we can also not control
the military with other means
it is a difficult institution but it's
an institution that
should protect us from outside threats
for example
you can hold the military responsible
for the failures when it comes to
fighting the corona pandemic
the military should certainly be the
institution that defends us from the
outside threats that's exactly don't mix
the military with the police
the police defends us against the
internal threats the military defense
against external threats
and external threat for example is a
pandemic so i think
the military would get a you know give
them something to do
and they're usually fine so if you give
them a little thing to do which is for
example to protect the territory against
the pandemic
you give them a new responsibility they
should actually take care of it should
be a military thing
that's that's what you should do with
the military i think i think when it
comes to weapons spreading
yes china and america are now so mad
they could go to war with one another
there could be war over
one in the next 10 years that's how bad
it's gotten it's not something john cena
krista
predicted 20 years ago we didn't think
the world would be as bad as it is right
now
we were as shocked as everybody else was
when xi and ping declared himself
dictator for life in china in 2014.
we didn't think the chinese leader could
be so stupid as to the clearance of
dictator for life
because the only way you get rid of a
dictatorship the killer will wait until
he dies
you get a north korean system and the
last thing the world needed in 2014
was for communist china to turn into a
massive huge communist north korea
that's exactly what china is heading
today that's why the system is unstable
and that's what's threatening to world
peace
the problem is that no matter who's in
the white house if it gives in to the
chinese which biden is likely to do
because it's corrupted by them
or if you place around like a little boy
with a bunch of toys like like uh donald
trump would
the problem is that any of these two
presidents could put america to war with
china
that's how bad the situation is that's
very real
because otherwise i would have said a
few years ago that the real threat in
the 21st century
is that the atomic bomb gets spread
across the planet and the people start
to be
innovative about it and then think they
can create atomic bombs that only have
local damage done and as soon as you
create atomic bombs that only do local
damage
and you put them on a drone the military
has got the new favorite weapon they're
looking for which is ascend the drone
and not sacrifice a single soldier's
life from their own army
but actually send a drone into the
community they're fighting and then kill
tons of people with an atomic bomb
the worst thing is though if you think
of the recipes it takes to create an
atomic bomb that iran saudi arabia and
turkey are chasing probably from corrupt
pakistan
engineers at the moment meaning the tank
bomb is very likely going to spread
this is still to me and john a bigger
threat to world peace than climate
change the biggest threat is still
the spreading of the nuclear bomb so
it's sort of a phallic pharmacome
we both believe in nuclear power more
than most people do when it comes to
solving the planet's issues
we also think the spreading of nuclear
bombs is a much bigger threat than
people have realized
so we're back at the 1980s and realized
that nuclear bombs is the biggest threat
of them all
because if you make a nuclear bomb in
the nearby future
in a more smart technology than you have
in the past and you put the nuclear bomb
on a drone
this is perfect for any terrorists to
set
up from anywhere in the world and
straight into a community full of people
and kick down not just skyscrapers but a
whole city
and then smither it all with nuclear
material
so i think that that threat is very real
and it's one of the problems when you're
advocating anarchy and openness on the
online world it's going to be that
you've got to fight these guys saying
that
well if you openness of blood we're
going to terrorist sex to create nuclear
bombs on drones very soon
i was like yeah so fortunately yeah
that's a major problem
one of the biggest problems of the next
100 years
all right so um one last question by
aurelian but before that can you just
for because nick
had an additional question just in a
couple of sentences could you expand and
what you mean with the bad
absolute the bard absolute okay the
it's not barred like my name it's not
b-a-r-d it's b-a-r-r-e-d
like enclosed okay the bard absolute
that's what it's called because the
opposite of that is the bard
subject in lacan in psych analysis
you don't have insight into yourself
your subject is invisible to you
so it's called the bard subject and the
opposite of that is the part absolute so
if you think of the bird subject
then there must also be barred objects
it's called the object
in in psychoanalysis shackle khan's
french meaning that
the object is never accessible to you
you chase it all the time
this is the one obviously chase it could
be another person you want to fall in
love with somebody it could be an object
you're obsessed with but you're always
chasing the
object an object that's prior to all
other objects in your life
so that's the part of it now if you just
move that to the next phase then you get
the barred absolute
and what that means is that the absolute
is the ultimate horizon
of your worldview like think of the
absolute most ultimate thing usually
people say god or something like that
but if you think through it thoroughly
that's not to be god but the absolute
absolute absolute ultimate arise of your
life is called the absolute
now imagine then that you live in a
culture where the elderly tell you
you don't actually have access to the
bar to the absolute it's barred to you
you cannot have access to it because
your subjectivity is barred then one of
the absolute
and this is foundational for the
religions called zoroastrianism judaism
whereas islamic christianity broke with
that tradition and islamic christianity
the absolute is accessible to us we can
all pray directly to god without going
to any go betweens that also means god
has absolute and direct access to us
for good or bad i would say that islam
is a religion where god has access to us
and we have to behave
and in christianity we have access to
god at all times so we can always go to
god and he will always be interested in
us and
if nobody else pays attention to our
tweets any longer and nobody gives us a
like any longer
god will sit there bored on his cloud
looked down on us and said
he likes everything we do see you know
unconditional love endlessly is the
question god right so if you have the
sort of vulgar idea of divine love
then that is there's no absolute there's
a bard
between you the absolute is accessible
to you
i think that is a dysfunctional idea of
religion operates
as a dysfunctional human beings operate
because
when you're a child adulthood has to be
barred from you
that's exactly what we don't give
pornography to kids so we don't want
them to be thrown into battlefields with
outer violence to kill people
we don't want our children to become
murderers and porn stars right
that's precisely because we keep them
out of the pathic realm until they're
grown up
enough to understand what that is that
means that
that realm is barred that means the
adulthood is barred for children it's
something they look up to and aspire to
and when they're ready for it they're
allowed to write a passage in our
culture
to go from childhood into adulthood and
the adulthood is no longer barred from
them
but then when you're an adulthood
there's certainly a lot of shamanic
practices
barred from you there's certain things
you're not allowed to do enough grown up
and they're for good reasons probably
so the elders and the shamans do certain
things you don't do as an adult and then
you move on
so the broad absolute is always what
escapes you
that you don't have the right to have
access to yet because you're not ready
for it in eastern philosophy it's called
sutra and tantra i think those terms are
wonderful
i think we need to introduce them to the
west properly to understand the shift
between the sutra and the tonjin but
this all deals with the bird absolutely
all right so now we got to the last
question of this wonderful evening
and it's a it's a very interesting
question
uh it lingered all the way through what
you were saying and
and it's beautifully expressed here
postmodernism in the terminology of
digital libido is a project of pure
multidinal death worship this is
antithetical to nietzsche's ideal of the
strong
and fearlessly independent men i guess
postmodernism
postmodernism often cites nietzsche as
one of its most
main inspirations but it seems he would
never want to be
associated associated with what they are
selling
so what exactly has happened here i
agree strongly okay it's a great comment
from meridian
i i usually say that postmodernism this
is this may
might be vulgar version of it since
nobody agrees over postmodernism is we
could just use it that way but
um hitler ein rund or post modernism who
was the most
vulgar misinterpreter of nietzsche
apparently nietzsche is a guide a lot of
people misunderstand
they also do that with hegel they also
do that with freud they also do the
marks and i've come to believe that it's
a sign of the grandness of this thinker
that they're being so misunderstood by
so many people because
there's something incredibly glamorous
about them because it's so
amazingly smart and productive so
they're great philosophers and that's
why they're being misunderstood
yes what nietzsche meant with this
relativism was
that he started to move the world around
so he started realizing that
there are relations in the world and
these relations actually dictate
how you value things and prior to
nietzsche leibniz did this
loudness did this with physics and it
did with biology this with the world
libras was the guy who said there is no
actual center to the world
the world is not spatial in that sense
there are distances between
objects and depending on which object
you start from
that will be the center of your study
but there is no center per se in the
universe
that was actually leibniz's genial idea
already in the 17th century
and if you follow all the way through
from loudness up to niche you realize
that nietzsche takes that sort of
relativism seriously
and he then attacks christian protestant
europe
for still being this sort of christian
platonist fantasy that he wants to
attack he wants to go after plato
and he also wants to go after what he
thinks is the mismanagement of that type
of culture
he wants to go after the sort of naive
platonist
we call this a peter pan syndrome
directed culture that he finds
and instead look for something much more
lively and thriving
and that's why he goes into the
dimension as opposed to apollonian and
he discusses donation apollonian
in our work that's a split phallus the
apollonian is then the priestly and then
the dimension is
chieftain so we have these roles as well
to split phallus that nietzsche talks
about and we then split them in smaller
parts that nietzsche didn't
that's what we do in our work so i agree
with you strongly nietzsche is heroic
and that's why i would never believe in
a culture
that ultimately says there are only
victims and this is just a race towards
the bottom that would be the total
opposite of everything nietzsche stood
for nietzsche is heroic he believes in
the ubermensch
and the ubermensch sets the standard for
everything
else in nietzsche's universe so there is
a fixed point in nietzsche's ideal
and that is to be and stay within the
heroic realm and stay here wrong no
matter what happens to you
and that's exactly why the most heroic
person is not the people born to be
heroes
these are people who fight and struggle
their entire lives and against the
elements
they establish themselves as being
heroic and this is where i'm strongly
needs him this was my opposition against
black lives matter i'm totally pro
martin luther king
i'm against black meta i think the shift
between these two guys is the same shift
we did
when the west in europe left marx and
went for rosso the same shift again
because it was difficult to stay in the
heroic people became
lazy and arrogant and went for
victimhood cults
the problem that the victim would call
tear us apart and will destroy us
so i want to finish this off by just
saying that the ultimate argument
against post-modernism is actually not
nietzsche's but it's the hegelian
argument
when post-modernism says that there must
not be
any single truth it has just declared
itself as that single truth
and that's when you should really watch
out for the tyrant and this lynch mob
all right well i think we
we got it alexander
thank you a lot for doing this this was
highly enlightening
thank you a lot tom for having me and
again kids
guys out there check out parallax i love
it i want to be part of it i want to
party building parallax definitely
right i also would like to thank all of
the participants and these great
questions
so um to keep this all lively and
ongoing
and i hope we will have a couple of
those events in the in the future
parallax events parallax lectures
building
our community building uh the academy
of strange and new thought and
well-thinking in the best possible way
so i wish you all a beautiful
uh what have you one mon monday monday
evening
and alexander you're uh
in stockholm now i'm in in palma and
from wherever you are i hope
you get through this weird year and this
crazy year and you're all fine and
thank you for participating
all right here you go there we go
there you go speak soon